Dr. [screaming]
Jared,
>> [laughter]
>> why are you laughing?
I just love the intro. I love the whole
setup, you know, I appreciate it. Yeah.
How are you, Dr. Ball? IT'S BEEN A LONG
TIME.
>> a long time. I'm as good as could be
expected. I appreciate the invitation.
It's good to see you and peace to your
audience.
Wait, what's this going on down here?
Did you draw a person with their arms
up?
>> Oh, I forgot that's in it. So, cuz I use
StreamYard, too. So, like No, like So,
so so shout-out. We don't work together
anymore, but I'll give him credit.
Shout-out to brother Diallo, and he came
up with the idea, and it's related to
our topic that like so so
that when people see
uh misrepresentations of buying power
and and so-called financial literacy, he
his argument was they should just throw
up the bat signal, the the buying power
signal,
and call for it call for me.
Uh and then uh
the rest of that's an homage to uh the
the the novel Snow Crash and and my
particular mixture. But anyway, yeah, so
yeah, yeah. Thank you.
>> [laughter]
>> Thank you. I did not expect all of that
to come out of that. THE MYTH AND
PROPAGANDA OF BLACK BUYING POWER
>> [cheering]
>> BY DR. JARED A. BALL.
OKAY, I'm really not going to do a lot
of talking
because I really feel like
I need you to explain this for folks cuz
I know that so many of us have been sold
on
black folks spend the most money,
right? And we have been sold on that as
a positive thing, and I know that as
someone who came from Hollywood, this is
before I divested from celebrity,
uh we were often told
the argument was always like, well, why
aren't we making black movies if black
people are spending the most money,
right?
And so that was really the argument, and
it WOULD BE LIKE, YEAH!
YOU KNOW, LIKE I really felt like when
people said that that I was in my right
to feel like, YEAH!
WE SHOULD BE! But then
as one begins to
decapitalize,
you begin to understand, hold up. But if
we have the most black buying power, as
they say,
then what the hell are we always Why the
hell do we have the least legislative
power? Why do we have the least economic
power? Why do we have the worst air? Why
do we have FEW WHY WE GOT TWO TREES in
the hood, etc., etc., etc.? So, long
story short,
um
I met Dr. So, let me also add, I met Dr.
Jared Ball
That's
Somewhere around 10 years ago, I would
think.
>> it's Well, it's No, it's way more than
10 years. Oh, really? Yeah, because I
was living in Harlem. I still lived in
New York, and I lived in
my apartment that I remember, and
um
I came down to talk to your class about
digital media.
And I was doing views I was doing uh a
show I used to do called Things I
learned this week. Yeah.
THAT'S I WAS A FAN. I've been I I I used
I
I still appreciate your work, but I I
have always loved that particular
uh effort
um because of what you were trying to
do, how you were doing it, the DIY, but
but with with production value. Yes. So,
the the the quick backstory to that is
that that was the one time I have ever
had access to a budget at Morgan State
University, and the last time I had
access
to budget a budget at Morgan State
University.
So, so uh
the short-lived effort that we had
going, the the goal for me was
to say, well, and there's a long
backstory to this that that that would
we don't need to get into right now, but
but um maybe of some interest at some
point, but the backstory included that
that I I was we were rebranding and
reshaping what would become what is now
the School of Communication. Yeah.
>> And uh they were building they built the
studio, they put in all this this this
uh
you know, relative amount of resources.
Yeah. And so I said, well,
but but I've never wanted to encourage
students to go into commercial media,
and that was always part of the
background tension with me and the
school. And so I was saying, well, if
they want to do this kind of work in
this kind of teaching, uh cuz admittedly
I'm more of a critical
theorist and historian than I am a
practitioner.
And so I said, well, fine. Well, I want
to I want to feature uh black people and
specifically black women who are doing a
version of media in this digital media
space that is something left of more
substantive than and something that we
could also reproduce. I mean, we don't
have CNN, MSNBC, etc. So, I was like,
this is So, I just thought what you were
doing was great. So, so I said, let's
let's let's bring you down and and and
have you engage with the students, and
it went very well. Uh to this day, I
think it's one of Bear TV's still
biggest viewed most viewed YEAH! BUT
THEN WHY'D THEY TAKE THE BUDGET?
That's a long story that has something
to do with what we're talking about
today, but it has more to do with with
me and my politics and
>> my fault?
No not real No, no, no, no, no, no.
Okay. You were I mean, it you did a
great job, I think, but you were you
were an emblem or or a symbol of what
was at core a problem for me and the and
the administration and the new
leadership that they were bringing in.
And
uh so it wasn't that you did anything
wrong. It was from their point of view
misapply misappropriate resources to do
things that were not
in their interest. This explains why a
year later I was supposed to come to
Morgan, and the day before they
canceled.
The day before. That's interesting, but
>> At that time,
like that was money that I needed. You
know what I'm You know what I'm saying?
Like I needed that. Like it wasn't like,
oh, like I'mma go buy me a Gucci bag. It
was like, oh, I can pay the last 3
months' rent that I hadn't paid now that
I'm going to do this appearance. And
they canceled the day before.
I don't have any information on that,
but it would not surprise me to find out
that there was some connection because
>> was a there was a there was a when I
like, you know, pressed it, it was like,
oh,
uh the they're high there was a higher
administrator who rescinded the
invitation.
They didn't know you were coming, now
they know you're coming, and they want
to use the budget for something else.
And I WAS LIKE, WHAT DO YOU MEAN?
LISTEN, OTHER than other than the the
gracious time you have afforded me to
talk about my book, I do I I'm going to
shamelessly promote this this project
and invite you and anyone else who would
want to participate as a as a as a
respondent to
just go to our mix what I like.org,
scroll to the bottom, and check out my
Not a Different World HBCU
memoir research project. Um because
I think a lot of what is often promoted
as a different world, pun intended,
particularly for those of a certain
generation and and TV remember memory,
uh is not, and there's a lot of
unfortunate political overlap between uh
white-dominant institutions and
uh institutions
>> .com? .org. It's mix what I like.org.
It's just my link tree, and then at the
bottom is is a link to to a video, and
then the link to where they can see more
about the project. And it's just
inviting you or anyone who has ever been
to an HBCU as a student, staff, faculty,
admin, or a parent uh to share some of
their their stories because I eventually
am going to talk about my
uh now 19 years
uh experience at Morgan, and um want to
share Yeah, it's been a minute. And to
share um
a little bit about what is again not
unfortunately the different world people
think it it is promoted to be, and and
uh which is in in some ways related
again to the topic at hand.
[clears throat] But uh I mean, I feel
like that's directly related because I
I want to get into how we see cap
capitalism within the black context is
counterproductive to black liberation.
So, when we see HBCUs that are operating
within the same capitalist um
framework as private white institutions,
predominantly white institutions, there
it's
you just got blacks in the same
situation, but with less money,
more politics,
etc. So, talk to us, what is the myth
of black buying power? So, you already
touched on what the myth is. The myth is
that black people have what is now said
to be approaching $2 trillion in buying
power, and if black people were more
financially literate and
responsible and mature, then black
people could use that to finance the
revolution and the closing of
generational inequality, and so on and
so forth.
>> Like Buy some land,
you know,
set up a business, you know, circulate
the dollar.
response to everything. You went out
there and bought some Jordans, you
should HAVE BOUGHT YOU A FARM. NOW, the
only thing I appreciate what you said, I
just put it put a salute to my my
radical African centered community and
uh that I do come out of in some way.
So, I want to show you know, the the the
popular version of the whole tap has
been you know, been been a drag on on on
my militant African centered folks. So,
I want to you know, leave some room for
you know,
you know, um but but in in and in fact,
what is actually interesting is that
because the myth has been so so
pervasive and powerful for so long, it
it it has impacted everyone in the black
community across the political spectrum.
So, I don't spend a lot of time on it,
but I do make reference to what I got a
kick out of is that for all the
so-called beef we've been you know,
taught about between Garvey and Du Bois,
Garvey jokes with Du Bois at one point
saying like, you know, homeboy welcome
to my side of things by recognizing that
we do have this buying power. So, in
other words, at one point they both
agreed on this. At one point Malcolm X
uh supported the mythology. And and as I
do talk about, one of the uh unfortunate
and I think unwitting
major purveyors of the myth is the late
great Dr. Amos Wilson from the very
again militant side of that African
centered community who was far from a
joke, but had mistakenly misread these
reports and claims and then tried to
adapt them to his more radical politics
and and and goals. But but uh
that's part of what the mythology is
meant to do. It's meant to take whether
you're a radical or a conservative, it's
meant to
uh have us all expend unnecessary energy
on what cannot be a solution.
So, So, what part of it is the myth?
Like, is is the myth that we spend this
money and thus we should be able to
really actually re
reappropriate it in a better way, but we
don't or is the myth also that we don't
even spend this money?
So, it's a little bit of both because
one of the problems is that I that I
discovered when I went into looking to
this is that all of the claims for
buying power since the early 1990s at
least come from really just one source.
Uh it's evolved into two, maybe three at
this point, but they all do the same
thing. And that's the Selig Center for
Economic Growth out of the Terry
Business School in the
the University of Georgia in Athens,
Georgia. And by its own statements, it
only exists to help Georgia's businesses
do better in reaching their target
audiences with their ad revenue.
And this is part of the problem. That so
so when so the myth is as you said, that
black people have this pool of resources
that are ignorantly misspent. But the
reality is
that the claims of this pool is based on
what as the Selig Center says in its own
reports, quote, estimates and
projections based on limited uh survey
data of a segment of the black
population's spending behavior.
So, it's not so so it's very important
>> in any way. No, there's
>> [laughter]
>> It's not it's not an accurate
measurement of what black people spend.
It's certainly not a measurement of
income. It's definitely not a
measurement of wealth. It's not a
measurement of what black people have.
It's a measurement of what potentially
black people have only to spend on
products and resources and services they
do not own and do not control, in some
ways need, but cannot be in control of
and then therefore use whatever wealth
will be generated to redistribute to
help the community and so on and so
forth. So, buying power, which is my
particular focus, is really a subsidiary
myth of the grander myth of black
capitalism, which is itself a subsidiary
of the grandest myth of capitalism,
which is that which is why I always like
to joke that the the most famous and
perhaps most powerful critic of of
capitalism was himself a white European
male, uh Karl Marx writing in the 19th
century talking about an almost
exclusively white context. And even in
that setting, he was saying capitalism
does not work. So, the idea that we
could then plug in colonized African
diaspora communities and say, "Now, you
can do it."
is is you know, so so is part of the
problem. So, what I do in the book is
just sort of try to trace relatively
quickly the history of the claim and
then show how at various points in
history it gets rebranded and
re-weaponized and then specifically used
particularly around the 1970s to target
black communities to rebrand as Nixon
wanted to, black power as black
capitalism. SAY IT AGAIN.
UH AGAIN, THIS IS NOT SPECULATION. This
is not Jared's opinion. This is this is
documented statements that Richard Nixon
wanted to rebrand black power as black
capitalism. He wanted to redefine it
away from any forms of nationalism,
socialism, radical pan-Africanism and
get everybody back on black electoral
politics into your point of your earlier
conversation, mainstream electoral
politics, not some alternative use. And
then the entrepreneurial vision. And
then this this as he understood would be
designed to uh undermine the righteous
desire of black and other communities to
free themselves and and get all that
energy put even when among well
well-meaning people. So, I'm not saying
[snorts]
[laughter]
people who advocate not everyone who
advocates for some
>> I don't mean to cut you off, but I'm
actually cutting you off. Is
Because you know like how you know
things intrinsically
and then it's confirmed. That's why we
need scholars etc. by the way, y'all
because like the affirmation also drives
you to keep doing the work that you're
doing because it also affirms for you
that you're not freaking crazy in the
midst of being gaslit. But I have I've
always known intrinsically
that there is an effort to push me from
way from being radical. Like there's a
very clear effort, right? And then I've
come through the school system and I was
really good at school, right? And I've
come through the uh higher education
system and I did the masters and all the
things. But it was still always like,
"Yeah, but like why don't you go and get
a job? Like you don't need to you know,
be like a
rabble-rouser etc. etc." And as I've
grown and matured and done more
research, you also are real you're like,
"Okay, so this clearly there the effort
to end
black radicalism aligns with the
explosion of black excellence. And you
see black excellence and you think black
radicalism, but if you are an actual
black radical, you know that that is not
black radicalism.
No, Kwame Ture was very clear. Black
visibility is not black power. I mean,
it's a great Ru Abaman, black faces in
high places will not save us. That's
right. And from the white capitalist
perspective, uh William F. Buckley said
of the Rockefeller plan to encourage
black capitalism,
uh scattered success breeds universal
hope.
So, yeah. I mean, so this is I mean,
they're very clear So, like this is so
so one of the few benefits that I've
always pointed to about getting the PhD
in media studies is that
it allowed me to sit down and in an
organized way study the history of the
field of mass communication, which is
really a study in the origins of US
propaganda and psychological warfare if
conducted properly. So, you know, there
was a little struggle around that too,
which led to similar bumps in the road
for me, but whatever.
But but but really what it what I'm
saying that to say that that
we should never be surprised or give
undue credit to the amount of effort,
time, energy, money, resources spent by
the ruling elite in
trying to figure out all the various
ways to manage a population they very
much intend to exploit.
So, one of the founders of of of that US
field of mass communications research,
Harold Lasswell, you know, said
something to the effect that the goal of
propaganda is not of course to change
the conditions of the community, but to
change people's attitudes to those
conditions. So, and he was a well-funded
researcher put to the purpose of
the the political ruling
economic and military intelligence elite
who funded and put together this field
of mass communication
specifically to develop techniques to to
study all the various forms of the
population and to turn Eastern Europeans
into good white people, to turn Negroes
into good American Negroes and American
citizens and to to bring in all these
different groups into
a level of consumption and labor and and
and acceptance of exploitation that
would allow for us to end up where we
are today, where as Forbes reported a
few months ago, 800 people are worth
$6.2 trillion. How do you have a
situation like that unless you, as from
their point of view, engage in what they
call communication is domination or or
create all the different people
>> I'm sorry? Media is king. Oh, yeah,
absolutely. When we see these no kings
protests, I'm like, y'all protesting the
wrong king. You need to be protesting
mainstream media. That's the king. I
mean that you you you make a good point
in in in so far as I understand it at
least that part of the problem with with
many of these protests including the
disparate liberal politics that are
sprinkled throughout it is that there
that there
there is an intent to by design give
them no political outlet. So, whether so
that's why I think it's important that
you and others engage in these
conversations about so-called third and
alternative power parties or very
various or different ways of engaging
electoral politics, however people want
to do it, because that is I think part
of
the the the goal here to limit the
radical
aspirations and and
what are considered options by black and
many other people who have a very
obvious and righteous justifiable
complaint about what's going on, but
really don't know exactly what to do
about it and then if they can just be
brought back in to support the next
corporate militarist Democrat from the
perspective of those who rule
this is it's it's it's it's a you know,
an unthreatening
gathering or set of
gatherings and effort, you know.
Connect this to Obama.
>> [laughter]
>> So
um
So, Barack Obama for for if if folks
remember
if or if ever read the work of Paul
Street and others, you know, Barack
Obama was was not a newcomer to anyone
who was
aware of of the Democratic Party
machinations going back into the early
1990s.
I had the benefit at the time in the
early 2000s of working with the late
both of them are now gone Glen Ford and
Bruce Dixon at Black Agenda Report
who Bruce in particular coming out of
Chicago, he knew the Chicago political
scene. He had been a panther. He had
been in grassroots politics all his life
and he knew Obama and the crew that was
funding him from going back, you know,
so when he and others and then Paul
Street's work started coming out and all
these other, you know, it was clear as
was said of of Obama much like what what
Nixon said of his efforts with black
capitalism that Obama was quote black
but not civil rights black. And if folks
remember when when
I used to watch um
um
the McLaughlin Group
and Eleanor Holmes Norton, I believe was
the woman her name was her name, I I
think. Not Eleanor Holmes Norton, I
don't know who I'm thinking of. Eleanor
not not the black politician, the white
woman journalist Eleanor
Clifton Cliff Cliff something like that.
She was the regular
Okay. white woman guest on the on the
panel or journalist on the panel, but
she said one day of Obama that he that
that in other words, he was safe to vote
for because he
didn't have he was black but didn't have
the baggage of slavery because his
father was Kenyan and not a black
American. Which I say by the way and
people get very angry, but I'm like,
that's not a made-up concept that I'm
just pulling out of my neck. Like they
look at him and Kamala
in the same context and it's not just
the baggage of slavery, it's the
responsibility.
Right.
No, that was her language just to be
clear. And even as a radical
Pan-Africanist, I'm I'm able to see how
people play different parts of the
diaspora against one another and do and
pull all this kind of nonsense and
that's exactly what they were doing. In
fact, there was even that George
Washington University study at the time
that showed that black women were only
willing to vote for him because he had a
black American wife of a certain
complexion.
That that that so there was even there
was a lot of and if people read the
David Garrow book about about Obama, I
mean I just the Rising Star book. I mean
it's a fascinating read that I think
lends a lot of credence to the line of
argument that we're making here about
how Obama was
a manicured, well-groomed, selected and
imposed neo-colonial product. And his
goal
I referred to it in in in in some work
that obviously, you know, nobody reads
or cares about. It's tucked away. No,
it's tucked away in some in some journal
somewhere, but I was talking about the
the issue of connected distance. And the
point being that they could promote him
as being black, but he's distant enough
from blackness and from certainly those
radical traditions that he can be he can
be made acceptable. And and
so yeah, so so so Obama was was the
point being and it was even written
about Andrew Sullivan, I remember at the
time wrote about it in one of the white
conservative, you know, that imagine
what this country can get away with when
the bombs are being dropped by a black
president. You know, the the the like
like like there was all this under and
then he of course was deployed. He went
throughout the African continent to tell
continental Africans, you know, the
problem isn't imperialism and and
colonialism, it's your corrupt
leadership. Then he went to North Africa
to speak to the Muslims to say, you
don't need violence to be to to to free
yourselves, you know, look at the United
States and how we freed ourselves with
non-violence and all this other kind of
stuff. Like he did all of the things
meanwhile deporting more people than his
predecessor and Trump after him and all
that sort of stuff like that. You know,
he he expanded war and drone warfare. He
expanded the gap between rich and poor.
He he was the most heavily funded Wall
Street candidate in the history of
politicians up until that point.
So, he was not
he immediately got rid of I remember
immediately like like my big thing was
watch how fast he moves away from the
Employee Free Choice Act and he never
said it again denying encouragement for
people to unionize. He, you know, I mean
he you know, he got rid of Tom Daschle
who was the last Democrat who said
anything positive about about universal
health care. Like he immediately
[laughter] he was like he was like, so
you know, and then he brings us in this
Republican health care plan
that that that everybody is still wedded
to and that that people allegedly
some are about to be on trial have
responded to in in some some
>> Wait, what? Wait, what?
Well, I didn't want to I didn't want to
disrespect your stream by by overdoing
it, but I was making but I was making a
reference to to the alleged actions of
Luigi Mangione.
That that
that what he was allegedly responding to
and I did read the book that he was
allegedly referring to when in the
inscriptions on his his his bullet
casings deny, defend, deflect or
whatever. I mean, he's responding you
know, the book lays out very clearly.
They are we we are wedded to a health
care industry that is by design here to
deny people the the the care that they
need so that they can increase the stock
value and the the benefits and bonuses
going to the administrators who who run
and own the insurance company. So
all that to say as all this relates is
that that that what has been at effort
whether whether I'm talking about mass
com or buying power or Obama has what
has been at a great effort here has been
the the the intent to redirect in as
many counterinsurgent ways black
rebelliousness and the rebelliousness of
any other community into very safe the
safe confines of areas that can are
already accumulated in power and can be
easily controlled. And as the 2014
Princeton study showed, this country is
is not a democracy. It is it is
electorally beneficial only to the
oligopoly or the oligarchy that
own the country. So, so by having
everybody come back and when Bruce
Dixon, I mean this is what Bruce was
right
in describing Bernie Sanders even as a
sheepdog for the Democratic Party. That
that you we can't keep having, you know,
all of our radical
aspirations are just drawn right back
into a party that is I believe you were
just talking about it earlier, Nancy
Pelosi is using to walk away with
hundreds of millions of dollars
while everybody's out here starving and
struggling. So, yeah.
Anyway. So,
when we talk about the myth of the black
buying power, right? The second part of
it was the myth that if black people
just had economic
not
the one that drives me crazy is if we
just had
financial literacy, we would
See? [laughter]
Listen, listen, I don't mean to I don't
mean to to to to overimpose
this this welcome you're giving me, but
please at some point and I Why do you
keep saying that? I don't know. I I
don't know. If I Do I seem like somebody
who would pretend? No, no, no, I don't
think you're pretending. I'm just saying
I don't want to ruin I don't want to
No, no, no, I don't want to You've
opened a door and I don't want to close
it behind me.
>> I would close it. I know, okay.
You're right. So, fair enough. So, so
fair enough. Absolutely. So, I apologize
for that. But I do that.
But listen, please check out the work of
future Dr. Erica Brown and she's a
co-host of a first of all great podcast
on on our collaborative effort Black
Liberation Media, but she does she
co-hosts a great show called Broke-ish
where she and her her her co-host Amber
talk about
black economics. But future Dr. Erica
Brown who is on her way working on her
PhD in in studying the history of of
this claim around financial literacy has
done a better job or is doing I think a
better job of
dispelling this mythology than I've done
with buying power. But it's a very
similar it's very similar in its in its
origin and and design. That is that she
has helped identify the origins of the
claim and the rubric used to determine
whether people do or do not have
financial literacy and then and then has
identified how it is itself being used
as a narrative as as as Dylan Rodriguez
says lexical warfare as as a narrative
claim against black people and other
poor communities to justify their
poverty by as a result of their own
ignorance.
And she and others have connected
financial literacy beautifully to the
tradition of literacy in general being
used by colonizers to say, "Oh, these
indigenous people, they deserve to lose
their land and all that cuz they can't
read.
>> [laughter]
>> They don't they don't know my language.
So, therefore they deserve So, financial
literacy works in many of the same ways.
And when you look at the rubric that is
used, you know, can you Do you know how
an IRA works? Do you know Can you
calculate quickly how much this stock
would appreciate? Like this is not why
people are poor cuz they don't like this
is
this is this
But this is what's used.
>> But they also put those in place to also
keep people from having any chance. No,
absolutely. But they're just but but the
point being that that they're not going
to address what really creates poverty
and inequality. They're just going to
create this narrative that can be used
to say you know, black people are poor
because they're financially illiterate.
And and if they just And then they have
prominent black figures running around
here saying, you know,
look, they just you know, John Hope
Bryant is one of my favorite the targets
for this criticism cuz he's he's always
you know, and and he Oh my goodness,
please everybody, please watch the
episode where he shows up on Broke-ish
and gets an education from these two
women in in about what he's supposed to
be the expert on and he doesn't like it.
But he says his whole thing is black
people didn't get the memo. And if we
just got the memo like all these other
communities and got our credit score up
to 700, we could be free. I mean, it's
basically I mean, it is absurd. But
they're well-paid. It's like a cottage
industry to to make these arguments and
and and and get funded and platformed to
to go out and teach financial literacy.
Remember that was part of the five the
$50 corporate spend after George Floyd
was killed.
The the the the corporate world came out
and said we're going to put up 50
billion to help the black community. But
when you looked at the fine print, so
much of it was about we're going to set
up financial literacy courses and make
small business loans and and and which
is again what Kamala Harris said was her
plan for black America. We're going to
get you into crypto and we're going to
get you into to $20,000 homes home loans
and stuff like and and small business
loans. And it's like this is not what
this is not why people's houses are
falling apart or their their communities
are are it's they don't need a $20,000
home loan. They need massive investment.
They need redistribution to your point
about socialism. That $20 gross domestic
product that this country produces every
year, that's what we should be targeting
for redistribution. Not some fantasy
about buying power and and you know,
small business and small this and and
Bitcoin that and all it's it's absurd.
It Yeah, so I That's how it all is
connected. And then and then with the
Obama thing, it's like, "See? Even in
this country, if you if you produce
even you black people, if you produce
someone as good as Barry,
you can be president. So, there is
nothing but there's no barrier here.
There's no racism.
What you complaining about?
>> [laughter]
>> I need you to know I get beat up on this
internet every day
for these thoughts.
No, I thought I had it bad, but then I
see you you know, you you you know. So,
like you go on So, like what I thought
was funny is that when I was thinking
about today is that you you go on um
Club Shay Shay and and at least in some
diabolically or perhaps at poorly edited
way in some cases get to get to offer up
your
I get my argument and book dragged on
Club Shay Shay by Killer Mike who goes
on there and cusses me out again in some
indirect way cuz he doesn't like my
argument or my book. So, that's what I
So, that's So, it's like a lower level.
Like you you YOU YOU LIKE
YEAH, you go face it and then and then
the backlash from it and all of that. I
get the very indirect like like And I
and I do poke fun at Killer Mike has a
real problem with me and my book, but he
he he So, he likes to
I think it's that that I'm challenging
The book does mention Killer Mike and
Jay-Z.
>> [laughter]
>> He's like, "I do say his name."
>> I do say his name.
But only to say only really to say But I
also say people that that that Not that
I hate him, but I also say people who
are my heroes like Malcolm X that who I
And my only point is to say that even
I'm not judging him as bad. I'm saying
they are misrepresenting even
unwittingly
this mythology and these claims. So, I
just try to point out how that happened.
And then it was a long story. He he
claimed he'd read the book and we had a
little disagreement in this that, but he
likes to from time to time go on other
platforms and and make hostile reference
to me indirectly.
And so, that's what I was That's why I
was just kind of laughing like cuz he
most recently went on on Shannon
Sharpe's show and and took another shot
at me again.
Huh? People still go on that man's show?
Yeah, come on. Well, that's kind of what
I thought, too. Like I mean, yeah, I had
a lot of different thoughts. But right.
But yes, they do and he did and then he
threw out his his little shot and
so, I'm like, "Yeah." So, on on a much
lower level
I feel what you're saying.
Um
How
Okay, so first of all, everyone, please
address your questions as I've put on
the scroll on the marquee to Dr. Ball. I
know you're going to have questions
because you talk very professorially and
folks is in the chat like
"Layman's terms." And I'm like
>> I'm sorry. Only one person did, but I
shut them down. I WAS LIKE, "STOP
CONTROLLING THE CONVERSATION." AND THEN
I THINK THEY went away.
Um but
what I really
I'm always trying to figure out, Dr.
Ball, is okay, we know this.
How do we shift it?
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> Right. Okay, ancestral
>> So, yeah, it's a very difficult I I
really do struggle with this. So, so
part of what I tried to do with the book
and I and I have some
regret is too strong a word, but I have
some, you know, some second thoughts
about my approach, but I was trying to
approach the topic without putting as
much of my politics in the book as
possible just to get people to focus on
the argument and the claim, not be
distracted by my radical politics which
sometimes historically has gotten in the
way of people being of hearing my
argument. With the idea of just saying,
"Look, if we we just need to get this
mythology out. If we can just get this
myth out of there, we can start to
figure out actual solutions. So, I I
kind of pointed to what I think we need
to do. I think that all public overt
so-called
legal work should be about addressing
the the pockets and and accumulated
resources and wealth and and target them
for redistribution.
So, at minimum, I think we need to be
saying to my point, "I don't care if my
financial literacy is low and I don't
care if I don't know anything about a
bank or a checking account or how to run
a business.
By simply paying bills, existing, going
shopping, going to work, I have helped
contribute to this 20 plus trillion
dollar gross domestic product. And I
want my cut. I want some free health
care. I want my housing decent. I want
some good education, some good food. I
want some some vacation time. I want my
my my
wage increases. All of these things
should be part of that And whenever
people say we don't have the money for
it, yes, we do. We have 20 plus trillion
dollars. We have 800 people worth 6
trillion. That level of inequality is
just inexcusable and unnecessary and
I've already contributed to it. Whether
I own the pizzeria, whether I'm buying
the piece of pizza, if that exchange
doesn't happen, nobody's making money.
So, stop treating me as a consumer in a
70% consumer-based economy as if I'm
somehow the problem and stop telling me
not to go buy my $10 latte and stop
telling me to get night Well, I can't
get my hair done anymore, but stop
telling me not to get my hair done. Stop
telling me not to get whatever we're
told They say, "Don't buy fronts and
your rims and your clothes and your $200
joy
Stop telling me that because if I don't
do that, the economy falls. If I don't
do that, people who work at Foot Locker
don't have a job and then they are nail
salon doesn't have a job and the hair
care people don't have a job. So, the
the issue isn't that I'm spending, the
issue is that all the wealth that's
being created from the spending gets
walked away with
a handful of people.
And so so I want us to get So, so that's
why I'm saying in the you know, we need
to join organizations, become more
politically radical, we need to become
more offline in some of these
discussions, but in terms of online
overt public conversation,
I want some redistribution. As I keep
joking, I know it's an older reference
now, but I'm very Frank White with it.
You know, if if if there's a nickel bag
being sold in the park, I want my cut.
And if there's money being made in this
country, I want my cut. I've already
contributed. We've all already
contributed. So, stop acting like I'm
asking for something that's undue.
Um so, that's why you know, and I think
that if if we get past some of this
mythology, if we learn more about how
the economy works and how we're being
exploited, I think more beautiful and
and sustainable solutions will be
evolved, developed.
So, you know, I want to that point, um
someone here said, "Okay, I agree, but
if you give us large sums of money and
we spend it on Louis, Prada, Gucci and
no land or investment in ourselves
aren't and we are at zero again, how is
that not a need for some kind of
literacy?" And so what I But I think the
operative part here is some kind of
literacy, right? So, like financial
literacy whenever we are So, I'm going
to say this and you tell me if you agree
or not. Financial literacy whenever it's
provided is always within the context of
capitalism. It's always in the context
of how do I just make myself win? It
never is in the context of how do I
understand the ways in which the the
economy of my community is being taken
and shift that to make a a community
economy that actually grows, right? So,
like that is the literacy that black
people would need and that is not the
literacy that is provided whenever we
are given full quote unquote financial
literacy. Am I right? I I think at least
in part you're right. I would want to
only add that that
I think actual financial literacy would
be to fully explain again how the
economy works and our relationship to it
and what what what then could be really
done about it. So, for instance,
uh with the example of Look, again, that
was sort of my point. If if if people
stop buying all the Gucci and the bags
and all of that, then the economy starts
to collapse and the people who work in
those stores and the people who work in
the trucking shipping lines that bring
the products to those stores Everybody
loses job. So, and the people who who
work in the store, they Everybody loses
So, you don't want people at least in
this economy, the argument shouldn't be
stop spending.
The claim then that we should use that
money and buy land is also part of the
mythology. If if as I
reference in my in my book, there's only
I think it was four or maybe five white
men that own more land in this country
than all black people combined.
Uh you know, Ted Turner has all the
land. So, like there ain't no land to
buy. And then when you And then when you
buy the land, again, this is on the
assumption that that black people have
this $1.8 or $2 trillion and that that
this is one pool of resource that could
be organized and then then this black
elected officials who would run this
this fund would then say, "We'll buy
this plot and So, that's not that's not
how it That's not how it works.
Secondly, for most people, including
businesses, to buy land, you need
investment or
a loan from another major white mostly
bank or institution. And then you're
paying taxes to a white government and
you're paying and you're paying you're
paying money to white-owned electric
companies and garage door opener
companies and like everything is like so
every So, so so you it
Anyway, so and then and then
And then even if you buy farms
Sorry. The money is still going out.
>> going out. And then if you buy farmland,
you're you What what crop are you going
to get enough investment in to to
produce enough of to sell enough of to
enough people to then create enough
wealth So, so again, this is that's all
part of the mythology. Again, it also
suggests that black people are poor
because black people spend too much time
buying bags and and and clothes and not
buying land. And that's not why black
people are poor and that's not how rich
people or white rich people or any rich
people got rich. So, that's part of the
misunderstanding of the economy. So, so
I I I That's why I'm saying if we get we
have to really get past this mythology
before we can start developing sound
logical responses
uh and plans. Now, you could always say
again, yes, if I only have a few dollars
left and the lights are about to be cut
off, okay, fine. It would be more
responsible to pay the light bill
tonight or today and then go hang out
with the next check you know, that's
fine. But that's not why people are in
that position in the first place. And
that's really the only point I'm trying
to make. We could all be a little more
whatever whatever, but but I don't want
to have to be super responsible and
frugal just to have health care or just
to have a decent place to live when I've
already contributed to a society that it
produces $20 trillion a year for those
who actually own the economy. And
>> It's the same It's the same argument
that the issue with the climate is
because of the individual carbon
footprint of you know, people not
recycling their Coke cans and not the
actual corporations who are contributing
daily on a regular basis to the use of
fossil fuels and emissions, etc. Listen,
I was in Desert Storm
in in 19 whatever whatever. In the army?
In the navy. I was in the navy. And I
remember them telling us I was on an
aircraft carrier. This is why I bring it
up. On the aircraft carrier I was on 30
years ago, they told us
every day
that one ship cost $1 million
just in gas. You know what?
A million a day just in gas. So, that's
30 years ago for one ship.
I'm not interested to your point about
being told to close my window or close
the refrigerator faster when they're
>> [laughter]
>> Right.
>> out here.
That's what's going on. Never mind what
they're out there doing that for. But
but
that So, you're right. We need This is
This is what Dr. King argued and is
often misrepresented for. This is what
every great person we've ever put up
There needs to be massive investment and
reformation of the society if we want to
actually address this inequality. If if
everything else is at the end of the day
smoke and mirrors and and propagated
nonsense. So, that's you know,
So, that's why I always ask, you know,
always more than ever we need to really
as a former former professor of mine
used to say, interrogate our
preferences. How do you know what you
know and why do you like what you like?
It it
No society in human history has put more
effort and has had more capability of
shaping those two
uh answers than ever. And so, I'm not
saying we need to change anything, but
just ask yourself, how did I reach that
conclusion? Cuz what is often the case
where we started we're we're working off
of mythology and misunderstanding and uh
and an absence of data and and and it
just so easily becomes
regurgitated mythology. And again, just
just look how often you I get a Google
alert almost every day on buying power.
Look how often or or how rare, if
anybody ever looks, that you see a
citation for the claim. Every They
people just say it all the time. We got
$2 trillion in buying power. Why aren't
we doing Where did you get that from?
And then when they do cite it, it always
goes back to the Selig Center, to
Nielsen and more increasingly the
McKinsey company, which is even more
diabolical given that company's history.
But none of it is meant to get black
people to better understand how the
economy works or what our relationship
is to it. It's only there to help
advertisers and corporations better
manipulate and and
um
shape our public opinion.
Are y'all listening? Cuz I tell them
this all the time. I'm like, please
think about why you know what you know.
How you know what you know. And nine
times out of 10,
it came from a source that has no
interest in your elevation.
None.
>> That's why I think I you know, I was
listening earlier, I think what you
you've pointed out before, but I think
it's important that you and I and others
are able to acknowledge that yes, at one
point I thought this and at one point I
did I learned.
And that's sort of the point that I get
at. So, like I get a lot, you know, in
some circles I've gotten a lot of grief
from from supporters of various people
that I mentioned in the book and I'm
saying I'm not hating on them. I love
Malcolm X, you know, uh uh uh So, I'm
not hating on him, but at one point he
misunderstood this, you know, uh
and that that's all I'm saying. These
are That doesn't mean everything else
about the man is bad or or you know, at
one point Amos Wilson miss I think
misunderstood this and I demonstrate and
show how I think he misunderstood this,
but that's only about this. It's not a
comment on his whole life's work, uh
which I find very valuable. So, it's
it's
>> it's To me, I find that endearing,
right? Like
>> a person whom you trust and who has been
proven to be bad at bad at, ride at ride
at, also misrepresented this or
misunderstood this, and thus, of course
your dusty ass did. You know what I
mean? Like that that to me is how I take
it. IF THIS MAN
>> EXACTLY.
WELL, no wonder I did.
>> Exactly.
So, the only one The only luminary, I do
like to shout him out for this and other
things. The only luminary that I could
come up with that that was always right
on this point was was George Jackson,
who who pointed out in his own work that
he called it out. They call it
purchasing power, and then they just
they rise they they raise the cost of
everything, so you it don't mean
nothing. And that's essentially what it
is. It's it's it's a measurement of your
ability to enrich others, and it's it's
not even an accurate measurement.
>> of your ability
to enrich others. That. Carry that with
y'all. It's a measurement of your
ability to enrich others. All right.
Well, before we go, we have some
questions from the audience. Can we do
that?
All right.
So,
uh Fatima says,
"Mr. Ball,
uh do you see a distinction between
individual wealth accumulation and
collective economic power? How should we
think about that tension?"
Well, the tension is that whatever we as
individuals accumulate uh
is it's almost like a zero-sum game. It
has no positive impact on the rest of
the community. So, I I you know, I it
So, so the tension is, if I understood
the question, that that we're encouraged
to chase our own individual
success, and we do that to the detriment
of the benefit of the whole.
So, it's it's in it's in some ways, and
I'm not an expert on this, so I don't
want to go too far, but it's in some
ways like a how I think people
I think game theory is in some ways
relevant here. That is that that that
rather Long story short, rather than
working together so that everybody
achieves the better conclusion option,
we are with the encouragement of massive
amounts of propaganda
uh
to to struggle individually and to to
achieve our own individual benefit.
That's why even I even hate that whole
thing of of if you want to change the
world, start with the person in the
mirror. Like I don't I get the
sentiment, but what it bothers me about
it is that is that
it it denies the collective need. It
denies the collective organizational
need and the collective movement need.
Um uh
uh and the need to work with and
convince others and and in some ways to
challenge others, which is one of the
reasons why I think sometimes my
argument has a little bit of a hard time
finding a hold because it it it
it says that I can't just do better
financially and and have that mean
something for the collective.
So, it's like when I joke, you know,
like in 2019, my wife and I bought our
first single-family home.
And how did that make any of you feel?
And how did that affect any of you?
Like
>> [laughter]
>> Well, I think some would argue,
"Well,
individual gain, and I'm just just um
individual If If you can take care of
yourself, then you don't require anybody
to take care of you. Or if people can
take care of themselves, then they're
not going to feel compelled to see to to
to theft or to crime."
Well, on some level, that's true, and
that was part of why Dr. King advocated
for a universal income and
uh
but it but but to the limits of of even
that level of of relative liberalism,
Nixon advocated for the same thing for
different reasons. Nixon wanted
universal income so that they could
reduce the social safety net and the the
the the the uh importance that people
would the weight
the the value people would hold for
government. And King was of course
saying, "Yeah, but everybody should
benefit more from what the government
the wealth produced for the government,
and it would reduce in some ways
people's tendency to to commit crime."
Like my I I joke all the time. I'm a
perfect example. I grew up in the the
lower end of the of the suburbs, the
lower end of the income end of the
suburbs. And as soon as I got kicked out
of the house, I was jobless and
homeless, it took me it it I immediately
went to crime. Immediately. That man
said immediately. Immediately.
Immediately.
Criminal activity. Now, I was terrible
at it, which is how I ended up in the
Navy, but that's a whole other thing.
But but but immediately. And so so like
like I can always think of that example
anecdotally as this is what happens. You
know, like I wasn't desirous of being
that way, but as soon as I did not have
somewhere to go that night, it was like,
"Oh oh oh no, something's happening.
Somebody got to come off of something,
like, you know." So, so you if you
extrapolate from that, of course. But uh
uh so that's what But that's But that's
really the the the the the point that
that that And then it also I think mis-
gets us to misunderstand how society
works. There is no I did it by myself,
and I don't need anybody else.
>> No. Even you know, you know, like we all
need someone to be doing something
somewhere else for us to have what we
what we want even when we're rich enough
to pay for everything.
So, I'm just That's why I'm trying to
get everybody to the extent I can back
on this whole collective thing. Like uh
uh
uh um
even the person doing the work we don't
want to do is providing something for
society and therefore should benefit
more from what society's uh
um accumulated resources afford.
So, yeah, somebody might have to do jobs
we don't want to do, but they should
also have to do it less to have more.
They should have more, you know, so so
whatever that job you don't want to do
it that it needs doing, let someone else
do it. Maybe three or four people could
be hired to do it, so everybody's paid
more and works less, and then everybody
has more time off, and then you know,
we could just start with that and then
see go from there. And this is what I've
been talking about lately is like we
have to actually think differently,
y'all. Like we I feel like, you know,
there's there's ways in which things
have been set up, and people are
frustrated that those ways are not
working anymore, right? Or they never
really worked, but they're they're like
completely falling into dysfunction. And
what I see so many people's argument or
desire for is like if we could just go
back, and I'm like it it wasn't better
before. It was just managed, right? So,
this could possibly This forces us to
imagine, you know, like a different way
of doing things
um that you know, has a an easier I
don't want to say easier, but that has
Okay, so you're done. Okay, so I thought
I was going to have to take the dog out
because he's been here complaining for
the past 5 minutes. Are you Can you lay
down?
Um No, like while you're talking, he's
over here like this.
>> [groaning]
>> I'm like, "What What's the issue?"
>> it's not me. He's not responding to me.
>> you. But I just feel like there's
there is something right about
Okay, I will speak individually.
Since like how you said you went to
crime.
Immediately.
That man said the it's the immediately
with your eyebrows raised. All of us
believe you.
>> [laughter]
>> He's like, "No, I stepped outside and
said, 'I'm robbing you.'"
Okay.
Um
I feel like when I'm in lack, I'm at my
most imaginative. Mm.
Like I
come up with that like it's innovation,
you know, necessity breeds innovation.
Like I am [clears throat] incredibly
innovative when
um I am in lack. I have not gone to
crime,
but I end up going to like my hands.
Like, "Okay, what can I make? What can I
What can I make?" And that's how I ended
up, you know, selling hand-painted bags
on MySpace to try to pay rent. And I
still got one of your paintings
downstairs. I just don't have that
multi-level cuz you sold one when you
when you came to Morgan. I bought one
from you when you when you came to
Morgan.
>> that?
Actually, I can't. And that's But that's
because we have guests, and that that's
a whole other thing. So, I can't I can't
at the moment. I should have I I should
have
Cuz I want to know what piece it is.
It's It's
>> wall. I want to say it's you DJ. It's a
woman DJ.
Is it? Yeah.
I I
>> I've painted so many things, I can't
even remember what Like people will show
me paintings, and I'm like, "I did
that?"
So, so yeah, I should have Yeah,
actually I should have had it ready cuz
it is downstairs, but I I um I didn't
think of it till just now. But that's
really it. I don't have the cuz I know
you you you you you know, poetry,
rhyming,
DJing, and comedy. I've done many things
only to come back to
basically selling selling pins on
Instagram, which is basically MySpace,
and talking for free, teaching for free.
That's essentially what's going down. We
have another question though before you
go.
>> Sure. Sure.
Dr. Ball, even though I said Dr. Ball, I
keep calling you Mr. Ball, but it's
fine. Mr. Ball, what are your thoughts
on the stock market, 401k matches, 529
for your kiddos' college? Like, are How
do we feel about these things?
>> Look, all of that is Look, so so I'm not
saying
don't have forethought, don't be mature.
You know, we're we're
We're putting money away for our kids.
We do You know all that kind of stuff.
I'm not I'm not saying don't do all of
that. All I'm saying is that's not why
black people are poor.
So, that that's all I'm saying. Not
understanding a 401k and not doing all
that, that has nothing to do with
poverty. So, if you you know, if if you
want to do a 401k and tacitly support
empire and the bombs dropping on kids in
Gaza, go ahead. I'm I'm doing it by
default cuz money is taken out from my
job by the state. So so I'm all you know
like but
So I'm not I'm not I would also say is I
noted in the book I think it's it's 1%
of the population owns more than half
the stock. So so stock is not a solution
like it's not you you we're not going to
invest our way to to to equality and and
and freedom. And if you're in the stock
market y'all like you can't even escape
being a part of uh if you're in it at
all you cannot really escape being a
part of like you said passively
you're you're you're BlackRock owns like
the whole thing.
>> That's what I'm saying. That's what I'm
saying. So like I'm like like do your
thing like if you if if
The first time that I had a business
manager this is when I was in Hollywood
and whatnot. Everybody gets a business
manager so I'm doing the thing that
everyone told me I'm supposed to do
right. So I get the business manager and
they're like we're going [clears throat]
to put you in mutual funds and we're
going to get you a SEP IRA and you're
like yeah I mean this is what you're
supposed to do. All right I'mma do it.
Like I am a big believer in this is not
my expertise and this is your expertise
so I'mma listen to you. So I I'm I'm
with them doing that whatever. Then some
whole thing happened and I end up going
to a different business manager. The
whole thing that happened was I got
scammed by people in China.
Oh wow. I got scammed but the business
manager did not protect me from being
scammed and I was like you need to come
up off the scam money.
>> [laughter]
>> Like you told me to send that check. You
told me to. I said is the money did the
money come and you said yes listen to
check and it hadn't. And now all of a
sudden you want me to read the fine
print. You're supposed to be the expert.
>> That's the reason why you get a cut.
That's right exactly. So long story
short I end up getting a new financial
advisor
a brother and he's like hey so you know
some of these mutual funds is private
prisons. WHAT ARE YOU TALKING ABOUT?
Yeah I mean look
So that's why that look I so I'm not
this is why by the way this is the same
thing you know it's the same thing in
terms of my my you know in other area
media criticism about So that's what I'm
saying I wasn't being critical of Jay-Z
and Killer Mike or any other artist or
any other person for for I'm not saying
you're a better you I'm saying the
decisions we're making are being
impacted by a set of ideas that have
been imposed by design for a long time
all to keep us from radical politics. So
it it's that's it. We all I I I fall
prey to it. I'm I'm you know we're all
caught up in this. I'm not saying I'm
sitting above this having solved
everything. I'm just saying this this is
what's happening. We got to find a way
to struggle against it and and work
around it or destroy it. And um
uh and that's it. So but I what I am
just emphatically wanting to re-
reiterate and say again and again and
again black people and no other
community for that matter are poor
because they don't know what a 401k is
and don't know how to set up a bank
account and all this other kind That's
not that's that has nothing to do with
the poverty. And it diverts the energy
away from where the energy should be to
actually
get us out of that.
>> I mean it's sometimes I've tried to say
like in class like imagine somebody's
just standing there punching you in the
face and then telling you you know like
>> how to do a roundhouse kick. Exactly. Or
or even even keep it in the same context
if you had set up a different if you had
invested more in your Roth IRA
IRA I wouldn't be swinging on you like
like it [laughter] doesn't make any
sense. Like this is that's not why
you're punching me in the face. Like
that's and doing that's not going to
stop you from punching me in the face.
And that's sort of the point that I'm
getting at. The reason propaganda is in
the title of the book is because that's
what it is. It is it and I try to give
some of the history and the context for
these for this for the propaganda and
the point of it and the function of it.
But that's why it exists to get people
to to in in in this most insidious way
to have black people blame ourselves
that black people blame
other black people for this horrific
condition. And that's what I want to
help
stop.
>> My my last question for you is what was
the difference between the second
edition and the first?
Well one uh
a little bit a couple of
tightenings to some arguments and some
arguments.
>> Huh? What was the time frame? 2020 and
2023 if you public it. The one of the
big differences is that Darrick Hamilton
wrote the forward to the second edition
and he's one of the leading black
economists in the country and
so I you know cuz I did I reached out to
a lot of economists like I'm not an
economist I'm a black studies media
studies guy so I'm only looking at the
difference between what is said and
what's the reality the data on you know
so I'm like help me out with the numbers
and no one ever said I was wrong but
most economists actually have always
said was buying power is not a thing
nobody uses it which is part of my point
as to why it's it's a it's a
specifically weaponized
targeted item for black people. Like
nobody is said like nobody is saying
what is the buying power of of this
community as as a way of assessing the
condition of that community and what
they might do about it. It's used for
other reasons but that's not so they're
like everybody was like yeah you're
right but
it's just not a thing and there's no
>> like oh like look at the Asian community
like the like particularly like the
Chinese community like the dollar stays
in their community 13 times.
>> Nonsense. Please so I don't deal with
that particular in the book that
particular claim as much but
in other work that I do and have been in
association with
I got to shout out
he goes by two black is also a poet and
an author has has done some of the great
work in dispelling that. My work and and
we all are referenced in a book by came
out last year by Ebony Reed and Louise
Story called 15 cents on the dollar
talking about the inequality in black
pay um where I and the whole thing about
Killer Mike is actually written about in
that book which is kind of funny. Um but
but but they talk about this mythology
the circulating dollar and talk and they
show how where it comes from how it's
false there's no such thing. The
the circulating dollar is it and they
challenge even the the mythology around
black Wall Street which is also
misunderstood. There's a lot of Oh yeah
there's a lot that that
>> of this book?
The Louis Well two black wrote a book
called Laundering Black Rage which I
think everybody should read and and and
check out. He also is a co-host of the
Black Myths podcast also on Black
Liberation Media. People could check
that out.
But then the other book is
15 cents on the dollar by Ebony Reed and
Louise Story who were
uh two formerly I think Wall Street
Journal journalists and Yale University
professors.
Um
I definitely encourage you to check that
book out please because they they show
you like the the origins I think her
name was Brooke Stevens who was where
where the
much like the buying power claim the
circulating dollar claim has a false
origin in a singular source that no one
can find or site and doesn't exist. No
economist use circulating dollar metrics
just like I'm saying no they don't use
buying power. It's all fugazi to get
specifically black people out of radical
politics and an accurate analysis of the
economy.
So
yeah please check that out. Absolutely
that's the book there.
That's the book there.
Damn it's like
Yeah.
It's like Dr. Ball like
>> Yep. Thank you. Yep.
I really
I BE RIGHT DR. BALL. [screaming] THAT'S
THAT'S THE BOTTOM LINE. Bottom of the
line.
That's really
I be right. I be
knowing.
>> [screaming]
>> And then folks like you come through and
be like yeah see.
Bing.
So I hope I hope the the bottom bottom
bottom bottom bottom bottom line that
folks get from this is
that that you then also have to keep
going with
is that there has been a deeply
concerted effort across multitudes of
mediums to simply just disconnect you
from black radicalism.
And the concept of black radicalism is
not radical.
That's a good point.
>> [snorts]
>> Like when you said like when you were
saying like oh you know you've gotten
like people not supporting you because
of your radical politics I meant to ask
you
what politics of yours are radical? Like
what are they calling radical?
What they're calling radical is that I'm
saying capitalism and black capitalism
won't do it.
>> Exactly. But that's it's not really
you're right. It's not really radical.
It's it's it's it's really pretty basic
and it's it's there's a lot of research
there's a lot to to add depth to that
argument but in short that's what it is.
That's all it is.
They just be you know
it's so much easier
I learned from being on Black and from
being on
um
uh what's it called Interactive One from
Radio One. I had a radio show on there
and then my show got canceled under the
auspices of Amanda is too polarizing and
not consistently funny.
Um I know though that I was canceled one
because I was pro-Palestine and
unshakable with it and two because I was
not willing to endorse Kamala blindly.
Like I was not going to tell everybody
to vote for anybody cuz I don't endorse
candidates. However I was also going to
call out Trump on a regular basis as
well as acknowledge when I felt that
that Harris was not showing up for the
people that she was, you know, getting
these votes for without question. And in
addition and and literally just that was
actively challenging black excellence as
a institution, right? Challenging black
capitalism as an institution.
Um that became like counter to a company
that pedals blackness as their main
like that's their whole thing. We're
black.
Listen, what We'll be We'll be the black
people in your ad
in your ad sales
um
port- portfolio.
What what
the what this society and others have
learned from a long, long time ago is
that it really doesn't matter what color
or
gender or sexual orientation the
ownership of media are. It's the ad
revenue that determines content. So, you
could have this very black, very woman
woman owning Radio One and TV One and it
does not change the content. It's
because it's not because she's a
specifically horrible person. It's
because even if she wanted to be a
revolutionary, she cannot be and have
any revenue to work with.
Now, she is a conservative woman. I
don't happen to agree with many of her
politics. That is Cathy Hughes and and
and many of her wasn't in the beginning.
Like she
>> But it doesn't But the point is is it
doesn't matter. It But that's how you
preserve. Yeah. No, that's what I'm
saying. If if you if you tomorrow became
the head of that entire network and
operation, it would just be undermined
and undercut with ad revenue. You would
just lose all your ad revenue. And
they'd be like then they would turn
around and say and add to the list of
things to complain about you that Amanda
can't run a network. Well, and then
there's also like now see your politics
is what got all these people fired I
mean what all these people laid off etc.
etc. etc. which Well, to your point, all
the all the research and shout out to my
co-host on Saturdays with Renee. Renee
called this out at the beginning and got
grief for it. But all the reports are
showing now that Kamala really lost
because because her stance on gossip.
So So like like
I
knew it
cuz that's ALL I WAS SAYING, DR. BALL.
THAT'S ALL I WAS SAYING. I WAS LIKE, IF
SHE GOING TO WIN IF FIRST of all, let's
let's just contextualize this as if this
was a legit election, right? Because we
First let's just pretend. But
you have I was like, you're going to
have to coalition to the left. Mhm. Not
to the right. You're going to have to
coalition to the left. AND PEOPLE WERE
LIKE, "SHUT UP, AMANDA SEALS. OH MY
GOD." SOMEONE THREATENED TO FIGHT ME.
Someone threatened Someone knew who I
knew in the past. Dr. Ball, she
threatened to come to my house and I
gave her my address cuz I am that girl.
>> Amanda. You Okay, wow. All right.
>> Come to the crib. I thought I was wild.
If you go
Well, you're the one that did crime. So,
you already lived that [laughter] life.
I said, "COME TO THE CRIB."
IF YOU IF YOU REALLY ON IT AND SHE SAID,
"OH, you live too far." CUZ YOU AIN'T
REALLY ON IT LIKE THAT. AND BY the time
you would leave, it would be a
re-enactment of the scene at the end of
Belly.
Oh damn.
That's why I invite ops to come to my
joint.
>> Oh damn. Come Come on. Let's talk.
Because Tommy Bonds was there with the
pistol.
Said, "I know you were coming."
Who put that pistol
>> Man, rest in peace to DMX. Rest in peace
to D'Angelo who's who's who's had a
track featured on that in that that
movie, Cuz the guys want the pie. Why is
why till we fry? Produced by DJ Premier.
Yep, absolutely.
>> to Primo. Yes, I forget who I'm dealing
with right here.
>> [laughter]
>> Absolutely.
That's So So no, absolutely. I I If If
I've been called
It's somebody This is a student at
College Park that threatened to
to to said, "I know MMA. Next time I see
you."
And all I was saying
>> I'll I'll come through with the
roundhouse cuz I I got a roundhouse kick
in my back pocket. Both legs, left and
right. I wish
to be the cliche 20 years ago maybe, but
I I I I I got I I got like 3 seconds of
fight time in me before the before the
ambulance is getting called for one of
us. Hey, listen. One time This is
completely irrelevant and now we're
basically on a FaceTime that people are
watching. But one time um this this
former manager I was at an event. He
tried to give me a hug and I was like,
"Hey, we not we not cool."
>> there yet.
>> And so then he called me a Like
literally just that's So my man at the
time was like
Come on, man. You can't do that.
>> [laughter]
>> And now I got to Now I got to go. So, he
was But the age difference was 29 and 30
and and 45, okay? That was the age
difference. So, he was like,
"We got to go outside, babe." So, he
heads outside. Also, my man at the time
is 6'3" and got out the pen like 6
months. So, he's very trained up, okay?
And when they came back in when he he
came back in by himself
20 minutes later and I was like, "What
happened?" He was like, "Man, this unc
sat there for 20 minutes pretending to
try to take his watch off."
>> [laughter]
>> That's not a bad move. Hold up.
He said the whole time Hold up. He was
like, "Unc, we don't got to do this,
MAN. JUST GO APOLOGIZE TO HER." HE WAS
LIKE,
>> [laughter]
>> "WE DON'T GOT
HE WAS LIKE,
"I DON'T WANT TO BEAT YOU UP. I WILL
BEAT YOU UP."
NO, BUT I'VE BEEN IN THAT moment where
you where you like, "Damn it.
>> [laughter]
>> I got to go out there."
So, now you got a new tactic.
This I'm Hold up.
>> [laughter]
>> This thing on
>> If I could just
Ooh, that ass whooping is right there.
Just
>> [laughter]
>> And then a car pulled up and he hopped
in.
And skirted. That's what he's doing.
He's typing on his
Hit me up quick.
>> [laughter]
>> Trying to get this watch on.
Got faiths to save.
>> [laughter]
>> Like
Oh, man. Dr. Ball, it's a pleasure. It's
been too long. It's all good. Yeah,
you're right. And and salute to you and
and your producer team and thanks for
the second chance cuz I missed the first
email. Yeah, thanks. No, [laughter] you
didn't miss the first email. I've been
trying to get to you, okay? I don't DM'd
you, but you're IN THE WORLD YOU'RE
LIVING in the world. You have children.
You have books to write. You're living
in the world.
It's It's It's all good.
>> Soledad O'Brien was LIKE, "OH, DR. BALL,
IT'S AND I WAS LIKE, "OKAY, WE HAVE TO
FIGURE IT OUT." AND I GOT YOUR NUMBER
from her.
Well, all right. Well, I appreciate it.
And thank you to all of you. This has
been great. Salute to your audience. And
since you played him earlier on your
show,
as I end all of mine, again, I just say
peace to you only if you're willing to
fight for it like Fred Hampton used to
say. And thanks again, man. This has
been dope. Appreciate you. Appreciate
you. Peace. Peace.